A Finding Aid to the Fletcher Benton Papers, 1934-2014, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bentflet
Archives of American Art
- Exhibition and Commission Files, 1959-2002; Series 4; 1.9 Linear feet Box 2-4, OV 11-13, RD 14
  - "International Working Symposium of Open Air Sculpture in Steel," Kleinwefers, Krefeld, West Germany, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Oversized drawings and plans moved to OV 12
  - Palo Alto Cultural Center, Exhibition and Lecture (1988), 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Double Folded Circle Ring (1992), Brussels, Belgium (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Contrats, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Photographs and Site Plans, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Oversized plans moved to RD 14
    - Commission's Files, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - Shipping Documentation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Video recording of Intallation, 1992; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Handwritten on the original box: "151 Boulevard Emile Jacqmain Unveiling of Sculpture Source B ref 2509" (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Gothaer Kunstforum, Steel Watercolor Triangle Ring (1993), Cologne, Germany, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Double Column, Ring, Triangle (1994), Arizona State University (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Video Recording of Installation of Balanced/Unbalanced Wheels #2 (1995), University of Nebraska, Lincoln, 1 Videocassettes (Betacam) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Double Circle Folded (2002) Cedars Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, California, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
  - Double Circle Folded (2002), Cedars Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, California, 2000-2002; Includes a rough edit of a promotional video on one videocassette (VHS) in folder 3. (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Oversized plans and drawings moved to OV.11 and OV.13 from Folders 1 and 2.
  - Film Reel from Box 2 folder 31 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Drawing from Box 2 folder 47 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Drawings from Box 3, Folder 12 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Drawing from Box 3, Folder 5 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 3, Folder 10 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 3, Folder 14 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 4, Folder 1 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Plans from Box 4, Folder 2 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Drawings and Plans from Box 3, Folder 19 (Box OV 12)
  - Oversized Plans from Box 4, Folder 2 (Box OV 13)
  - Oversized Plans from Box 3, Folder 11 (Box RD 14)
  - Oversized Plans from Box 3, Folder 23 (Box RD 14)
- Printed Materials, 1959-2006; Series 5; 2.3 Linear feet Boxes 4-6 and OV 10
  Series is arranged by type of material, and chronologically within each type. Newspaper and Magazine Clippings were originally organized in adhesive album pages but were removed during processing due to preservation concerns. Original album pages were photocopied to preserve the original arrangement. Additional printed materials can be found in series 4, Exhibition and Commission Files.
  Series contains printed material related to Benton's exhibitions and commissions. There are international materials in German, Japanese, Korean, Dutch and Spanish. Types of material include newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition catalogs, magazines, published books, brochures, posters, leaflets, press releases, and postcards related to exhibitions and commissions. Scattered magazines, books, and press releases referencing Benton's exhibitions are filed with exhibition catalogs, along with institutional collection catalogs unrelated to a particular exhibiton. Exhibition-related printed material consists mainly of exhibition announcements, but posters, brochures, and programs are also found.
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Oversized Clipping moved to OV 10
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1990-1997 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 2000-2006 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Includes NY World's Fair Art'65 and Lesser Known and Unknown Painters/Young American Sculpture-East-West
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Includes Los Angeles Engineer / Scientist, June 1966
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Includes Flint Institute of Arts Light and Movement exhibition; Whitney Review 1966-7 catalog, and Contemporary American Painting and Sculpture by the Krannert Art Museum, University of Illinois
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Includes Selection 1968, University of California, Berkeley
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
    Includes Constructivist Tendencies, University of Santa Barbara, California
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    /includes Public Sculpture / Urban Environment Catalog, Neubert, G., Oakland Museum, CA
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes program from San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's First Artists' Soapbox Derby
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Includes California Sculpture Show Catalog, International Arts Foundation, Los Angeles, CA, and Works in Bronze: A Modern Survey Catalog, Sonoma State University, Rohnert Park, CA
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes Fletcher Benton: Sculpture and Watercolors 1980-1986, with introduction by Jan Butterfield.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Includes the book Motion Motion: Kinetic Art
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Includes Picasso, Gravuren, und Fletcher Benton Skulpturen, Mathias Spital, Rheine (Nov-Dec, 1990)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Includes Ohioana Quaterly, Vol XXXVII, number 3, Fall, noting Benton's receipt of the annual State Career Award
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Includes Fletcher Benton, Tascende Gallery catalog, February-June, 2001
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Includes Fletcher Benton: Sculpture, Reliefs, Works on Paper, Neuhoff Gallery, NY
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Oversized material moved to OV 10
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Oversized poster moved to OV.10
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Related Printed Materials, 2000-2003 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Modern Mode Advertisement, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Oversized advertisement moved to OV.10
  - Oversized Materials from Box 4 Folder 5 (Box OV 10)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 5 Folder 31 (Box OV 10)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 6 Folder 7 (Box OV 10)
  - Oversized Materials from Box 6 Folder 16 (Box OV 10)
- Broadcast Materials, 1973-2001; Series 6; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Broadcast materials consist of a variety of sound and video productions including radio and television programs featuring Benton, documentaries, promotional videos, and exhibition-related programs. Material is on two sound cassettes and ten videocassettes (U-matic and VHS).
  Television footage includes an interview conducted by Paul Turner for a special program on KQED celebrating their Auction Art Awards from 1973-1975, news footage from the installation of the public sculpture Folded Circle-Arc from WQAD in Illinois, and an interview for WDAF-TV about Benton's exhibition in Halls' Gallery in Kansas City. A radio program is also found from Frankfurt's local radio, in German, about his work during the early 1980's in Germany.
  Additional video programs include a distribution copy of a documentary about Dr. Wennesland, for which Benton did a short interview; an extended interview conducted by George W. Neubert in relation to Benton's work between 1964-1974; and a California State University production where Fletcher Benton discusses his kinetic work with professor Jim McManus. The latter tape also includes a short video about computer artist Grace Hertlein. Good Time to be West is a documentary about twelve California sculptors and the relationship between their work and the region. American Artists in Jewelry is a short documentary about the exhibition held at the Gilman Baker Gallery in Boca Raton, Florida, in which Benton and DeWain Valentine participated, among other artists. The Lollipops: A Kinetic Sculpture by Fletcher Benton includes an interview with Benton talking about his sculpture and its mechanical operations. There is also one sound cassette that contains the soundtrack from an unidentified television program with an interview of Benton.
  Television and radio programs are filed first in the series, followed by documentaries and exhibition-related material. Additional audiovisual material includes a home movie in series 1, Biographical material, studio and artwork documentation in series 7, Photographs and Moving Image Materials, and raw footage and production materials for a documentary in series 9, An American Artist video recordings.
  - Television Interview, KQED, 1975; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; handwritten note on the cassette: "KQED TV Interview 1975 Benton"; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Original; handwritten note on original cassette: "KQED" (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Television News Footage of Installation of Folded Circle-Arc (1980), Muscatine, IA, 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Original; handwritten note on the original box: "News Story and Video Footage Shot by WQAD TV Moline, ILL. Fletcher Benton Sculpture, Stanley Consultants, Muscatine, Iowa, September 12, 1980"; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; hadwritten note on the cassette: "Benton Sculpture Installation Muscatine, Iowa, 1980" (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Radio Interview and Other Broadcast Material, Hessischer Rundfunk Hr2 (Frankfurt), 1981; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on cassette: "Hess Rundfunk2. Programm, Prisma. 10 July 1981"; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on cassette: "Hess. Rundfunk II / 7.1.81. Portrait des amerikanisieren bildhauer Fletcher Benton. von J. Leisegang" (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Television Interview, WDAF (Kansas City, MO), 1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Handwritten note on box: "Halls Interview. WDAF TV CHANNEL 4 KANSAS CITY (FOX) 04/10/97 12:00PM NEWS" (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Dr. Wennesland, An Icon Among the Beats, By Gerd Hennum, 2001; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Fletcher Benton: Selected Works 1964-74 International Video Corporation. Dessaisset Art Gallery and Museum., 1975; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Introduction to Art. Part One: Fletcher Benton, kinetic artist / Part Two: Grace Hertlein, computer artist, 1973-1975; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Good Time to be West, 1984; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate material; original not found with collection (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - American Artists in Jewelry, circa 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Lollipops: A Kinetic Sculpture by Fletcher Benton, circa 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sound from Unidentified Television Interview, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Photographic and Moving Image Materials, 1960-2005; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 7 and 9
  Series includes photographs and moving image documentation of artwork, exhibitions, inaugurations, and images of Benton in his studios. Images of the artist include photographs, motion picture film, and video taken in Benton's studios on Bloxom Street and Dore Street in San Francisco. Moving images of Benton's studios include a promotional video about the Dore Street Studio by Dave Hatch and a student film by Al Wong about Benton's studio at 63 Bloxom Street (1967). Images of artwork include photographs and motion picture film of paintings, sculptures, and kinetic works. David Finn's pictures are digital prints of Benton's sculptures created for the book Fletcher Benton (2003) by Carter Ratcliff.
  Personal photographs of Benton and his friends and family are found in series 1, Biographical Materials. Additional moving image materials are also found in series 1, as well as in series 4, Exhibition and Commission Files, series 6, Broadcast Materials, and series 9, An American Artist Video Recordings.
  - Images of the Artist (Box 7)
    - Studio Photographs, circa 1960-circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bloxom Street Studio Footage, 1967; 1 Videodiscs (DVD) Duplicate; 1 Film reels Original; Ektachrome; handwritten note on the original film can: "1967 By Al Wong (63 Bloxom St SF)" 16mm (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Film Reel moved to Box 9, Folder 2; DVD also contains digital copies of films found in Box 2, folder 31 and Box 7, folder 9
    - Dore Street Studio footage, 1984; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Handwritten label on video cassette: "Professional Sample Dore St. Studio" (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Dore Street Studio Photographs by Leo Holub, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Oversized photographs moved to Box 9, Folder 5
  - Images of Art Work (Box 7)
    - Paintings, circa 1950-1961 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Sculptures, 1965-1997; Includes 1 film reel: 16 mm; original Kodachrome; handwritten note on original can: "Fletcher Benton Retrospective of Early Works. Bronte St" (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Film Reel moved to Box 9, Folder 3; digital copy available on a DVD filed in Box 7, folder 6.
    - Kinetic Drawings, 1968-1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - David Finn Pictures, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 11-15)
    - Sunset Magazine Pictures, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions, Installations and Inaugurations, circa 1960-circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Film Reel moved from Box 7, Folder 6 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Film Reel moved from Box 7, Folder 9 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Photograph moved from Box 7, Folder 7 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Artwork, 1969; Series 8; 1 Items Box 7 (Box 7)
  Editioned art Christmas card created by Benton for Galeria Bonino in New York.
  - Miniature Synchronetic Christmas Card, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- An American Artist Video Recordings, 1995-2003; Series 9; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 7-8
  Series consists of 13 videocassettes (VHS) from the production of the documentary Fletcher Benton: An American Artist by Morgan Cavett, who was Benton's cousin. Being production material, there is a substantial quantity of footage that was not used in the final documentary, which is available on Benton's website and on DVD. Some of the material is personal and filmed in a casual manner.
  The full, unedited interview with the curator George W. Neubert and Fletcher Benton's interview at the Davis Symphony Hall comprise two video cassettes each. An interview and footage about the Homage to WWII Airplanes series is also found on two videocassettes.
  Three videocassettes contain footage of San Francisco's North Beach area with comments from Benton about his first years in the city, along with interviews of two of his studio assistants, Michael Roby and another unidentified assistant. Local scenes include Vesuvio Cafe and City Lights Books. Footage also includes studio scenes, some still shots of sculptures, and a tour given by Benton of his studio. Additional footage of the Dore Street studio and Benton's Napa home is on two videocassettes, and two rough edits of the documentary are on two additional videocassettes.
  Additional video recordings are found in series 1, Biographical Materials, series 4, Exhibition and Commission Files, series 6, Broadcast Materials, and series 7, Photographic and Moving Image Materials.
  - George W. Neubert Interview, 1995-2003; undated; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Fletcher Benton Interview at the Davis Symphony Hall, 1995-2003; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Homage to WWII Airplanes Series, 1995-2003; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - San Francisco North Beach Area and Assistants Interviews, 1995-2003; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Dore Street Studio Materials, 1995-2003; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rough Edited Versions, 1995-2003; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 8, Folder 2)